<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godlie and short discourse shewing not onely what time the inhabitants of this land first receyued the Christian faith: but also what maner of doctrine was planted in the same. Whereby may appeare, howe the reformation at this day in England is not a bringing in of a newe religion, but a reducing againe of the olde and auncient fayth.</title>
            <author>Rosdell, Christopher, b. 1553 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837406</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1004:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godlie and short discourse shewing not onely what time the inhabitants of this land first receyued the Christian faith: but also what maner of doctrine was planted in the same. Whereby may appeare, howe the reformation at this day in England is not a bringing in of a newe religion, but a reducing againe of the olde and auncient fayth.</title>
                  <author>Rosdell, Christopher, b. 1553 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Christopher Rosdell.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The ancient faith of England.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Godlie and ſhort diſcourſe, <hi>ſhewing not onely what time the</hi> inhabitants of this land firſt receyued the Chriſtian faith: but alſo what maner of doctrine was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Whereby may appeare, howe the reformation at this day in England is not a bringing in of a newe Religion, but a reducing againe of the olde and aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fayth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ierem. Chap. 6. verſ. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand in the wayes and behold, and aske for the old way, which is the good way, and walke therein, and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſoules. —</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe. 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:2"/>
            <head>To the right honourable and <hi>his verie good Ladie and Miſtres,</hi> the Ladie Fraunces <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Hertford,</hi> Chriſtopher Roſdell wiſheth increaſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and endleſſe felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an opinion (right honourable and moſt vertuous Ladie) not ſo true, as commonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and holden of a great manie, that the doctrine, faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Romaniſts profeſſe and maintain, is the olde and ancient religion, ordeined of God, witneſſed by the Prophets and Apoſtles, and practiſed of all the godly from time to time: and that the doctrine or religion now profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in England, is a new doctrine, which had his beginning but hereby. Which imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conceipt of theirs doeth by ſo much the rather pleaſe them, for that by ſome hundred of yeres laſt paſt, the true &amp; ſyncere doctrine of the Goſpel being ſuppreſſed, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and in a maner extinguiſhed, the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, or rather the hereſies of the later Church of Rome, haue euerie where both flowed and flouriſhed. Wherby it is come to paſſe, that like as a true and naturall mother, that hath beene long abſent from hir houſe
<pb facs="tcp:1725:3"/>
and familie, at the length turning home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, is not knowen, no not of her owne children: euen ſo, the ancient and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call religion hath beene ſo long abſent, and lacking to her Chriſtian children, that nowe at her returne ſhee is almoſt a ſtraunger to all, and in deed knowen but to a few. Hence commeth it, that although vnfitly applied, yet vſually it is ſayde of Romiſh ſuperſtition and idolatrie, The old Religion, the old Religion: and of the Euangelical doctrine of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, The newe Religion, the newe Religion. Not for that it is ſo in deede, but becauſe it ſeemeth ſo vnto them, who haue ſo long ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon their golden God of Rome, that they haue cleane forgotten poore and ſimple Chriſt Ieſus of Nazareth: Whereas if men would reade the Scriptures diligently, iudge indifferently, and ſpeake vprightly, they ſhould ſoone perceiue, that neither our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is newe, as they falſely charge vs, nor theirs olde and auncient, as they vainly boaſt of. For in them we are taught the true, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, and moſt ancient faith and religion of the Patriarches, Prophets, and holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. As that therefore which concordeth with them can not be newe: ſo that which diſſenteth from them can neither bee true nor olde. The Lorde by the Prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 6.16.</note> Stande in the wayes and beholde, aske for the old way, which is the good way, and walke therein, and ye ſhall finde reſt for
<pb facs="tcp:1725:3"/>
your ſoules.<note place="margin">Hiero. lib. <hi>2.</hi> com. in Ier.</note> Which place Saint Herome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth thus, Wee muſt cleaue vnto the Prophets, and diligently behold and aske for the olde and euerlaſting wayes, which more ſignificantly in Greeke are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the good way conteyned in the Goſpel: we muſt walke in that, which when it is found refreſheth and purgeth the ſoules of the faithfull:<note place="margin">Ad Pomp. cont. Epist. Stephan.</note> To the ſame effect S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſayth. <hi>Si ad diuina traditionis caput reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamur, ceſſat omnis error humanus, &amp;c.</hi> If wee would returne vnto the heade of diuine tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, all humaine errour ſhould ceaſe, &amp;c. If a water pipe (quoth hee) which before ran copiouſly and plenteouſly, doe vppon the ſudden giue ouer, doe not men go vnto the fountaine, that there the reaſon of the defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or giuing ouer might bee knowen, &amp;c. Euen ſo it behoueth the miniſters of God at this day to doe, keeping the diuine precepts: that if in any poynt the truth be changed or ſhaken, we might returne vnto the originall of the Lorde, the Euangelicall and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call tradition, that then the reaſon of our action might ariſe, from whence the order and originall hath proceeded. Thus farre Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. Excellently therefore ſayth S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, <hi>Antiquitas mea Ieſus Christus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Philad. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitat.</note> Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is my antiquitie. And Ambroſe alſo, We do rightfully condemne all thoſe new things which Chriſt hath not taught: for Chriſt is the way vnto the faithfull: If Chriſt then
<pb facs="tcp:1725:4"/>
hath not taught that we teach, we iudge euen that alſo for deteſtable. Hereunto Cyprian in another place. If Chriſt only be to be heard, we ought not to regard what anie before vs hath thought meete to be done, but what Chriſt who is before all, hath firſt done: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought we to follow the cuſtome of men but the truth of God. O that according to this rule we might be heard, our cauſe deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the quarell ended: then woulde it ſoone appeare, howe vnder the viſard of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, they haue hidden a new ſtartvp ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: yea that their whole pretenced religion is nothing elſe, but a huge heape of hypocriſie, and a ſtore basket of all Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Then ſhould it be ſeene, that this refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is not a declining from the auncient faith, nor a bringing in of a newe: but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing againe of the olde, and Apoſtolicall faith or religion. For the better profe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (moſt chriſtian Ladie) I haue in certaine of their chiefeſt holdes compared their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions with the cenſure of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and auncient Fathers: to the ende that the indifferent Reader might partlie iudge by theſe, what is to be thought of the reſt? In publiſhing whereof I haue had ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reſpect vnto the profite and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the common and vulgar ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: that they might haue, not onely at a ſmall charge, in reſpect of the price, but alſo with litle loſſe of time in reſpect of reading,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:4"/>
whereby they might bee either inſtructed, if they were ignorant, or the better confirmed if they had ſome knowledge. And theſe my labours whatſoeuer they are, I am right well aſſured, ſhall be by many degrees more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and acceptable vnto diuerſe, for that they proceede and come foorth vnder your honourable name and protection. Moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie therefore I beſeech your honour to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſame in ſo good part, as with a good will it is preſented vnto you. Whereof as I nothing doubt, ſo will I neuer ceaſe to pray vnto the almightie, that you may long liue in this worlde to his glorie, and the benefite of his Church: and finally after this life, may for euer reigne with Chriſt Ieſus in his immortall &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glorie, Amen. December the 15. 1588.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours faithfull ſeruant, and Chapleine, Chriſtopher Roſdell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1725:5"/>
            <head>The firſt planters of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Realme or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of England, if it were not (as Cardinal Poole in an Oration made in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t houſe, <hi>Anno 1554. Nouember. 28.</hi> importeth) of all other Ilands y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt that imbraced the faith of Chriſt: yet that it was worthie (for the antiquitie therof) to be numbred among the firſt, may by diuerſe and good teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies be ſufficiently prooued.<note place="margin">Nicepho. li. 2. cap. 40. Gildas de victo. Aurel. Ambroſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> ſayeth, that Simon Zelotes came into this Iland of Britaine, for ſo was it then called. <hi>Gildas</hi> ſaith, that Ioſeph of Aramathie, which begged the bodie of Ieſus, after the diſperſion of the Iewes, was ſent of Philip the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, from France to Britaine, about the yéere of our Lorde 63,<note place="margin">Anno. 63.</note> and here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in this land all his time, and ſo with his fellowes, laid the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:1725:6"/>
of Chriſtian faith among the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine people. Whereupon other tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and preachers comming after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Beda.</note> confirmed the ſame. And for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proofe hereof, that is to be obſerued which <hi>Beda</hi> teſtifieth of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that in his time and almoſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yéeres after Chriſt, here in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, Eaſter day was kept after the maner of the Eaſt Church, to wit in the full of the Moone, what day in the wéeke ſoeuer it fell on, and not on the Sunday as the Church of Rome did then, and we do now. Wherby it falleth out moſt likely, that the firſt planters of religion in this lande, came out from the Eaſt parts of the world where it was ſo vſed, rather then from Rome where it was not ſo vſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapter. What ſucceſſe the Goſpel had in this land at the firſt.</head>
               <p>YEt notwithſtanding, becauſe wée find no certaine relation of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reformation, &amp; profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1725:6"/>
faith in this lande, both by prince and ſubiects, vntill the time of Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius Biſhop of Rome, and Lucius king of this lande: thereby it is very probable and likely, that albeit the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and trauailes of thoſe auncient fathers, which firſt turned vp the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of Idolatrie, and ſowed the ſéeds of pure religion in this lande, albeit (I ſay) their labours were not vnfruitful, yet they preuailed not ſo farre foorth, as vnto an vniuerſall and publique refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation throughout the whole land. So hard and difficult a matter it is to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the minds of men, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in through long continuance they haue taken déepe roote. Thus alſo it pleaſeth God to worke that by degrées, which he coulde bring to paſſe all at once, and to finiſh that by one, which was begunne by another. And ſo he brought that (as it were to a perfect building in this lande) by the miniſterie of Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, whereof hee had laide the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Simon Zelotes, Ioſephus, or ſome other Apoſtolicall men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:1725:7"/>
               <head>The third Chapter. How Religion increaſed and was confirmed.</head>
               <p>THe ſéeds of true Religion being thus in ſort &amp; meaſure ſcattered here and there by the miniſters of Chriſt in this poore diſtreſſed land, were ſhortly after by the malice of Satan, either vtterly choked, or elſe ſo repreſſed, that vntill the time of king Lucius ſonne of Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus which builded Colcheſter, which was about the yéere 180.<note place="margin">Anno. 180.</note> they beganne but little to appeare foorth vnto the world. At which time the ſayd Lucius (then king of this land) hearing of the great miracles and wonders done by Chriſtians of that time in diuerſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, directed his letters to Eleutherius Biſhop of Rome, to receiue the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith. Who hearing the requeſt of this king, and glad to ſée the godly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of his well diſpoſed minde, ſendeth him certaine teachers and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers called <hi>Fugatius,</hi> or by ſome <hi>Fuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Damianus,</hi> or <hi>Dimianus,</hi> which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1725:7"/>
conuerted the king and people of Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and baptized them with the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and Sacrament of Chriſts faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter. What publike alteration folowed this generall conuerſion.</head>
               <p>THe inhabitants of this lande being thus turned from their diuerſe and many gods to ſerue one liuing God, true religion with ſyncere fayth increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſuperſtition decayed, prophane temples, with al rites and monuments of Idolatrie were ſubuerted, and the whole ſtate of the common wealth was now cleane changed and altered. For whereas before this time there were in this kingdome 28. head Prieſts which they called Flamines, and thrée Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts, which were called Archflamins: hauing the ouerſight of their maners. and as it were iudges ouer the reſt, Theſe 28. Flamines they turned to 28. Biſhops, and the thrée Archflamines, to thrée Archbiſhops, hauing then their ſeates in thrée principall Cities of the
<pb facs="tcp:1725:8"/>
Realme: that is, in London, in Yorke, and in Clamorgantia, <hi>videlicet Vrbe Legionum,</hi> by Wales. And thus the Countries of the whole Realme, being diuided euery one vnder his owne Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and all things ſetled in good order, the faith of Chriſt continued here the ſpace of 216. yéeres, till the comming of the Saxons into this lande, who then were Pagans and heathen people, by whom the faith and faithfull people of this land were ſuppreſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The fifth Chapter. What maner of doctrine was at the firſt planted here.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe many thinke that the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and faith which is now taught in this realme is not the ſame which at the firſt was planted here, by Simon Zelotes, Ioſeph of Aramathea, or ſome other of their felowes, whoſoeuer they were that firſt inuaded this land, by the ſword of Gods word to ſubdue it vnder the obedience of Chriſt, and afterwarde was confirmed by Eleutherius his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1725:8"/>
but that it was many hundred of yéers ſince deuiſed by mans inuention, and through the might of humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie thruſt vpon the people: and that the doctrine now taught and holden at Rome, is the olde and ancient doctrine, which firſt was planted here by thoſe Apoſtolicall fathers, and after was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, augmented or ſetled by Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius Biſhop of Rome: I ſuppoſe it will not be altogether vnprofitable in ſome and the chiefeſt points of doctrine to ſhew what was the faith, iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and opinion of the godly learned in the ancient &amp; primitiue time of the church. For ſuch faith, iudgement, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as was in them, no doubt they did not onely by vocall preaching, labour to perſwade in others, but alſo in their writings haue left behinde them for all poſterities to ſée and knowe. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are none either for antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more to be reuerenced, or for fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more to be truſted, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles of Chriſt our ſauiour, we will eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enquire after their faith and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and comparing their iudgements
<pb facs="tcp:1725:9"/>
with the faith &amp; doctrine of the Church of Rome at this day, we ſhall ſoone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, not onely how much they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from the ancient faith of Rome, but alſo how néere at this day we come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame. And that this reformation or alteration of religion in England, is not the beginning of any newe Church of our owne, but a renuing of the olde ancient Church of Chriſt, not a ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from the Church of Rome, but a reducing to the true Church of Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixt Chapter. Of the Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction of the Biſhop of Rome.</head>
               <p>ANd firſt to begin with the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall iuriſdiction of the Biſhop of that Sea, which they affirme at this day to extend it ſelfe, not only ouer all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, kingdomes and prouinces of the world, but alſo ouer al eſtates, degrées, ſynods, and aſſemblies of men. When the diſciples contended amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note place="margin">Mat. 18. Mar. 9. Luke 9.</note> who ſhould be the greateſt: good occaſion was offered vnto our Sauiour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1725:9"/>
(if he had intended any ſuch Hierarchie or ſupremacie) then by ſhewing whom he would aduaunce to that dignitie, for euer to haue decided this queſtion. But as one intending no ſuch matter, hée perſwadeth them rather in perfect hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and lowlineſſe of mind one to goe before another. In deed after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, hee gaue them commiſſion, ſaying, Go into all the world, teaching all nations, &amp;c. but no where, nor at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time did hee ſay to them, or any of them, Goe to Rome, Antioch, or Hieruſalem, and be thou intituled or inſtalled there for Biſhop, that thou mayeſt be prince of Prieſts, ſupreme heade of the Church, my vicar vppon earth, not to bee iudged of any, hauing all knowledge of Scriptures &amp; lawes within thy breaſt, and that I giue to thée, I will alſo tie and binde my ſelfe by promiſe to giue to all thoſe ſhall in that place ſuccéede thée. And as Chriſt no where gaue any ſuch prerogatiue to any of his diſciples aboue the reſt: ſo did none of them euer vſurpe or take vpon them any ſuch matter. Yea the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:1725:10"/>
Peter was ſo farre from chalenging vnto himſelfe any ſuch prerogatiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his felow Apoſtles, that he did not onely giue the right hand of felowſhip to Paul,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> but alſo was content to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued by him. And as for the Church of Rome, there was no more reſpect had vnto it in olde time, as appeareth euidently by the teſtimonie of Pope Pius the ſecond,<note place="margin">Ex Epiſt. Pij ſecundi. 301</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to other churches. But euery Church was then ruled by his owne gouernance, till the yéere of our Lord 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.<note place="margin">Anno. 340.</note> Then folowed the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of Nice, wherein was decréed, not that the Biſhop of Rome ſhould be vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Biſhop, chiefe prieſt of the worlde, prince of the Church, or any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but that the whole vniuerſitie of Chriſts Church, which was now farre ſpred ouer all the world,<note place="margin">Ex concil. Nicen.</note> ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed in foure prouinces or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts: whereof euery one ſhould haue his head church and chiefe biſhop, called then Metropolitane, to haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of ſuch Churches as did lie about him. In the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of which patriarches or Metropolitanes, the biſhop of Rome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1725:10"/>
had the firſt place: not for any dignity of the perſon of him that then was biſhop, or of him that ſuccéeded, or of him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is ſaid to ſucceed, but onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place wherein he did ſit,<note place="margin">Ex Concil. Calc. ca. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as moſt plainly may be proued by the Councel of Calcedon, which ſaith, Our fathers did worthily attribute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe degrée of honor to the ſea of old Rome, becauſe the principall raigne or emperie was in that city. The ſame alſo is confirmed by <hi>Euſeb. Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex Gabriel Bicl. lect. 25.</note> declaring that the excellencie of the Romane Emperie did aduance the Popedom of the Romane Biſhop aboue other Churches. Moreouer the ſaid <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> ſaith, the councell of Nice gaue this priuiledge to the Biſhop of Rome, that like as the king of the Romanes is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Emperor aboue other kings, ſo the biſhop of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame city of Rome ſhould be called pope aboue other biſhops. Thus although the B. of Rome, for the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; excellency of that city, had the firſt place giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him, this was don by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s authoritie, &amp; not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie of God. And all this notwithſtanding he had no more, nor greater authority the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other
<pb facs="tcp:1725:11"/>
Metropolitans: but euery of the 4. had his peculiar circuit and precinct to him peculiarly apointed,<note place="margin">Ex Concil. Conſtant. cap. 36.</note> in ſuch ſort as one of them ſhould not deale within ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers precinct, and alſo that there ſhould be among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equalitie of honor. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we reade ſo oft in the decrées of the old cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, equal degrée of thrones, and of honours amongſt Prieſtes and miniſters. And againe ſpeaking of the ſaid Patriarkes,<note place="margin">Conc. Con. cap. 2.3.</note> or Primates, we reade in the Councell of Conſtantinople, that Biſhops ſhould not inuade the dioces of others without their borders, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found togither Churches. The old doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors alſo for the moſt &amp; beſt ſort of them accord in one ſentence, that all Biſhops placed whereſoeuer in the Church of God, be of one merit, of like honor, and all to be ſucceſſours together of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. For <hi>S, Hierome</hi> ſayth plainly <hi>Omnes Epiſcopi pares, &amp; haeredes ſunt ſedis Apoſtolicae.</hi> That is, Al Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are equall, and are the heires of the Apoſtolicall ſea. And by examples he ſheweth, that the Biſhop of a ſmall towne hath like authoritie as a Biſhop
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1725:11"/>
of a great citie. And that if one Biſhop be higher or lower then another, it is becauſe one Biſhoprike is richer or poorer then another, otherwiſe they are all the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles. For this cauſe when Victor, which was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome <hi>Anno 200.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anno. 200</note> went about to excommunicate the Eaſt Churches for the obſeruation of Eaſter day, hée was not permitted by Ireneus ſo to doe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when Boniface the firſt required of the Biſhops of Carthage, to ſende vp their appellations to the Church of Rome, he was not only denied thereof,<note place="margin">Con. Cart. 6</note> but alſo the learned and godly men of Carthage, aſſembling themſelues in a Councell to the number of 217 Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, made a publike decrée, that none out of that countrie ſhoulde make anie appeale ouer the ſea. Yea the fathers in that Councell by their letters exhorted the Biſhops of Rome, that he would not induce the ſwelling pride of the worlde into the Church of Chriſt, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and giueth the light of ſimplicitie and humilitie to ſuch as loue to ſée God &amp;c. And after this, about the yéere of our
<pb facs="tcp:1725:12"/>
Lord 583.<note place="margin">Anno. 583.</note> When Ioannes Biſhop of Conſtantinople went about to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh that proude title of vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to the ſea of Conſtantinople, the Biſhop of Rome that then was,<note place="margin">Ex Palagi. 20. dſti. 99. cap. nullus. Ex Anton. tit, 12. cap. 3.</note> called Pelagius the ſecond, &amp; his next ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour Gregorie the firſt, were ſo farre off either from giuing vnto the Biſhop of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople that proud title, or from chalenging it to themſelues, that when it was offered by certaine Biſhops vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gregorie, hée refuſed it ſaying, none of my predeceſſours were ſo arrogant, as to vſurpe this proude title, calling it newe, fooliſh, proude, peruerſe, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, prophane, &amp; ſuch as to conſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, is as much as to denie the fayth. Yet for all this, there is no one thing for the which the Biſhops of this later Church of Rome doe more egerly fight and contende, as may appeare not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the decrée of Boniface the eight, wherein he commaundeth euery man, vpon paine of damnation, not onely to beléeue, but alſo to be ſubiect to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie or ſupreme authoritie of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope. But alſo by that they doe euery
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1725:12"/>
where burne thoſe for heretikes which acknowledge not the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenth Chapter. Howe the Biſhops of Rome in olde time were ſubiect to ciuill Magiſtrates.</head>
               <p>AND as in olde time the Biſhops of Rome kept themſelues within the bounds &amp; limits of their own prouince and precinct: ſo were they alſo as wel as all other eccleſiaſtical perſons, ſubiect to their Emperors, &amp; lawful magiſtrates: yea, and that not onely in cauſes ciuill, but alſo in eccleſiaſticall gouernement. <hi>Gregorius</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Magnus</hi> was ſubiect to <hi>Mauritius,</hi> &amp; called him Lord, ſaying, you were then my Lord, when you were not Lorde of the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire:<note place="margin">Gregor. ad Mauritium, Auguſt. lib. Epiſt. 3. Epiſt. 61.</note> behold Chriſt himſelfe ſhall make you anſwer by me, which am his moſt ſimpleſt ſeruant and yours. And before him Eleutherius his predeceſſor biſhop of Rome, writing to Lucius king of this realme, calleth him by the name of Chriſts vicar. Boniface alſo the firſt by
<pb facs="tcp:1725:13"/>
humble ſupplication obteined of Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius his Emperour, that a lawe was eſtabliſhed, none ſhould be made Biſhop of Rome by ambition.<note place="margin">Diſt. 97. ca. Eccleſiae. ca. Victor.</note> Iuſtinian alſo Emperour of Rome, ordeined and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted many wholeſome lawes for the ordering and gouernement of the Cleargie, as that no Biſhop or Prieſt ſhould excommunicate any man before his cauſe were knowen, and proued to be ſuch, as for the which the auncient Canons of the Church woulde him to be excommunicate. And if any ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe procéed contrarie to the ſame, then the excommunicate perſon to bée abſolued by an higher degree, and the excommunicator to be ſequeſtred from the Communion,<note place="margin">24. q, 3. cap. dc illicita.</note> ſo long as it ſhould be thought méete by him that had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof, &amp;c. Beſides theſe, many other ſuch like examples (if it were not to auoyde tediouſneſſe) might be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But ſéeing the queſtion groweth to this iſſue, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhops of Rome, ought by the diuine law of Gods word, to be ſubiect to their lawful magiſtrates or not, we will omit and ceaſe to heape
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1725:13"/>
vp a multitude of examples out of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s law, and produce a fewe witneſſes out of the worde of God. And firſt of all, Chriſt our Sauiour did not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund his diſciples to giue their allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to Ceſar, but alſo himſelfe paide tribute. And the Apoſtle Paul writing to the ancient Romanes ſaith.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule be ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higher powers, vnder whoſe obedience, neither Pope, Cardinall, Patriarch, Biſhop, Prieſt, Frier nor Monke, is excepted nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted,<note place="margin">Theophil.</note> as <hi>Theophilactus</hi> expounding the ſame place declareth, ſaying. Hee teacheth all ſorts whether he be Prieſt or Monke, or elſe Apoſtle, that they ſhould ſubmit themſelues vnder their Princes. And <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> writing <hi>ad Bonifacium,</hi> ſayeth in ſuch like ſort. Whoſoeuer refuſeth to obey the lawes of the Emperour which make for the veritie of God, incurreth the danger of great puniſhment.<note place="margin">Aug. contra Creſco. lib. 3 cap. 5.</note> Alſo writing vnto <hi>Creſconium,</hi> hee hath theſe wordes. Kings, according as it is inioyned them of God, doe ſerue God in that they are kings, if they in their kingdome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
<pb facs="tcp:1725:14"/>
thoſe things that be good, and forbid things that be euill, ſuch as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine not onely to humane ſocietie, but alſo to Gods religion. Vnder the olde Teſtament, were not the Prieſts and Leuites ſubiect to the ciuill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, yea euen in matters of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall gouernement, when king Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid diſpoſed them into foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie orders or courſes, appointing them continually to ſerue in the miniſterie,<note place="margin">1. Para. 23. &amp; 24. &amp; 25</note> euery one in his proper order and turne as came aboute? And when good king Ezechias renued the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Cleargie being decayed.<note place="margin">2. Para. 31.</note> 2. <hi>Parapo. Chap.</hi> 31. But the Byſhop of Rome at this day with his ſhaued Cleargie can not in anie kinde abide to bée ordered or diſpoſed by any, and therefore iudge good Chriſtian Reader, whether wée or they in this reſpect come nearer vnto the auncient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Primitiue Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1725:14"/>
               <head>The eight Chapter. Of iuſtification.</head>
               <p>NOw as we haue heard how the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Biſhops in former time nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exempted themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their lawful magiſtrates, nor cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged vnto themſelues any vniuerſall iuriſdiction ouer others: ſo let vs alſo in other points of their religion &amp; doctrine compare them with the firſt and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue time, and we ſhall moſt plainly ſée they are altogether vnlike vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And here to begin with the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of iuſtification: firſt the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in al their writings, and namely Paul the doctor &amp; teacher of the gentiles, ſetteth forth no other meanes for iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or remiſſion of ſinnes, but only faith aprehending y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body or perſon of Chriſt Ieſus crucified. For as there is no way into the houſe, but by the doore: ſo is there no comming to God, but by Chriſt alone, which is by fayth. And as the mortall bodie without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſuſtenance of bread and drinke can not but periſh: ſo the ſpirituall ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:1725:15"/>
of man hath no other refreſhing, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by faith in the bodie &amp; blood of Chriſt Ieſus. And for this cauſe it is ſaide, To him doe all the Prophets witneſſe, that through his name,<note place="margin">Acts. 10.</note> all that beléeue in him, ſhall receiue remiſſion of ſinnes. Hee that beléeueth in the ſonne hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> and be that obeyeth not the ſonne,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> ſhal not ſée life, but the wrath of God abideth on him. For by grace are ye ſaued through faith, and that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God. When the kéeper of the priſon at Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippos aſked Paul and Silas, what he ſhould doe to be ſaued, they anſwered him,<note place="margin">Acts 16.</note> ſaying, Beléeue in the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt bee ſaued. With this Charge, and to this end our Sauiour ſent foorth his diſciples into all the world ſaying, He that beléeueth and is baptiſed ſhalbe ſaued, but he that will not beléeue ſhall bee damned. So Paul witneſſeth, that hee was called and ſent of God to call the people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that they might receyue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Acts 16.</note> and inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them which are ſanctified by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1725:15"/>
fayth in Chriſt. Thus the Apoſtles preached, and thus were the olde Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes (to whom Paul ſent a worthie Epiſtle notably deciding this queſtion) taught.<note place="margin">Acts. 10.</note> The ſame did Cornelius a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and firſt that was baptiſed of all the Gentiles, learne of Peter, when he receiued the holy Ghoſt, not by his own workes which he did according to the lawe, but onely by hearing the fayth of Ieſus preached. And in this faith and doctrine, not only the Church of Rome, but the whole congregation of Gods people continued many yéeres, as more plainely may appeare by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of theſe ancient fathers.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. li. 5. de orat.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, it is not the lawe but the faith of Chriſt that congregateth the Church: for the lawe is not of faith, but the iuſt by fayth ſhall liue. It is fayth therefore and not the law that iuſtifieth: for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe commeth not by the law, but by the fayth of Chriſt, and he that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth fayth, and preſcribeth the workes of the law,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de vita beata. lib. 1. cap. 6.</note> declareth himſelfe to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, for the iuſt by fayth doth liue. And the ſame father in another
<pb facs="tcp:1725:16"/>
place ſayth, This is that which profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me: namely, that we are not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the works of the law: therefore I haue not wherein I may glorie or boaſt in my workes, and for this cauſe I will glory in Chriſt. I will glory not for that I am iuſt, but for that I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemed: not for that I am without ſin, but for that my ſinnes are forgiuen me; not for that I haue profited any, or any hath profited me, but for that I haue an Aduocate with the father, euen Chriſt that ſhed his blood for mée.<note place="margin">Cyprian de paſsione domini.</note> 
                  <hi>Saint Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> writing vpon the paſſion of Chriſt, ſayth, The gift could doe more than the tranſgreſſon, and grace more then ſinne, for grace through the benefite of loue, hath fréely without any merite abſolued vs that were bound with the debt of condemnation.<note place="margin">Origen lib. 3 in epiſt. ad Romanos.</note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe words of the Apoſtle (We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man is iuſtified by faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the déedes of the lawe) ſayth: The iuſtification of faith onely is ſufficient, ſo that if a man beléeue onely, he is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, albeit no worke as yet hath bene fulfilled by him: and ſo hee alledgeth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1725:16"/>
the example of the théefe.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Pſal. 70.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vpon the 70. Pſalme, ſayth. The grace of God wherby we are fréely ſaued with out any our merits, is commended in this Pſalme. And a little after, Séeing then we are deliuered not by our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but by his grace, let vs praiſe him vnto whom we owe our ſelues wholy whatſoeuer we be.<note place="margin">Hiero. ad Galat. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> writing vpon the Epiſtle to the Galatians, ſaith, that neither Moſes, nor any other famous man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ancient fathers, could be iuſtified before God by the law.<note place="margin">Gregor, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ezech. Hom: 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſayth, Let vs not truſt in our wéepings, nor in our workes, but in the allegation of our Aduocate, who liueth and reigneth with the father, in the vnitie of the holy ſpirite.<note place="margin">Fulgentius</note> 
                  <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God crowneth in his ſaints, that righteouſneſſe which he gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fréely, and wil preſerue fréely, and will fréely make perfect. <hi>Maxentius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Maxentius.</note> we ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely beléeue that from Adam to this day none hath bene ſaued by the ſtrength of nature, but through the gift of the grace of the holy ſpirite, in the fayth of the name of Ieſus, for there is no other
<pb facs="tcp:1725:17"/>
name giuen vnto men vnder heauen &amp;c. Item, all the faithfull from Abel vnto Chriſt, as many as haue beene ſaued, haue béene ſaued by the ſame grace whereby we are ſaued.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in ſerm. de fide &amp; lege na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> fayth, I can ſhew thée a faithfull man, who without his good déedes, both liued and obteyned the kingdome of heauen: but none without faith hath had life, &amp;c. And leaſt here thou ſhouldeſt ſay, hee wanted time, &amp;c. I will not contende with thée herein: but this one thing I dare boldly ſay, that fayth onely by it ſelfe did ſaue him.<note place="margin">Baſil. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione de hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militate.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſile</hi> likewiſe ſaith, this is perfect &amp; true glorying in God, when any is extolled not for his owne righteouſneſſe, but acknowledging him ſelfe to be void of true righteouſneſſe, is iuſtified by fayth onely in Chriſt.<note place="margin">Bernard orat. prim. omnium ſanctorum.</note> And finally <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, What can all our righteouſneſſe be before God? Shal it not bee as the Prophet ſayth, like a menſtruous cloth? And if it ſhould bée ſtrictly iudged, all our righteouſneſſe ſhould bée found vnrighteous. What then ſhall become of our ſinnes, ſéeing our righteouſnes is not able to anſwer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1725:17"/>
for it ſelfe. Therefore let vs earneſtly cry with the prophet, O Lord enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant: and with all humilitie let vs flée vnto that mercie, which onely is able to ſaue our ſoules. By theſe teſtimonies (gentle reader) thou maiſt ſoone perceiue what was the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the godly learned in old time touching iuſtification. And in this faith the Biſhops of Rome with their Romaniſts ſhould ſtill remaine, if they were ſuch ancient Catholiks as they pretend, and if they would follow the olde mother Church of Rome, and hold the firſt liquour, wherewith they were firſt ſeaſoned. But the ſweete ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, &amp; ſent of that liquor, is now cleane put out, through other vnſauerie infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Popes thruſting in, ſo that almoſt no taſte, nor péece remaineth of al that primitiue doctrine which Saint Paul and other Apoſtles planted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The ninth Chapter. Of good workes.</head>
               <p>ALbeit the godly fathers in auncient dayes (as hath beene in the former
<pb facs="tcp:1725:18"/>
Chapter ſufficiently declared) nowhere could find any ſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort for the ſoule, or reſt &amp; peace of conſcience with God the Lord, but through grace and ſwéete promiſes of God, giuen to mankind in Chriſt Ieſus his ſonne. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they were not only abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruitfull in good workes themſelues, but alſo moſt vehement and earneſt in calling vpon all true faithfull people to ſerue the Lord in true holineſſe &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe before him all the dayes of their life, as by their liues and ſermons may ſufficiently appeare. For to this end are we elected, created, called, and fréely iuſtified to do all ſuch good works as God hath prepared for vs to walke in. Hereunto tend many exhortations, both of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Apoſtolicall fathers which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded them, not onely by order of place, but alſo veritie of doctrine. The like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of whoſe teaching if we doe not now folow, let our ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, preachings, writings, exhortations, and liues alſo beare record. For although we exclude good works from the office of iuſtifying,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1725:18"/>
yet we exclude them not from the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe and conuerſation of Chriſtian life, but moſt earneſtly call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Chriſt to walke worthie their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to lay downe their old conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to giue their members ſeruants of righteouſneſſe, to offer their bodies to God a liuely ſacrifice, &amp;c. In déed we do not (after the maner of our new found Romanes) ſet foorth for good works the deuices of men, as prayer for the dead, going of pilgrimage to dumbe idoles, reckoning vp of a certaine number of prayers to ſome certaine Saints, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of rewards, or building of Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries for to pull ſoules out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and ſuch like, which becauſe they neitheir haue commandement nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in the worde of God,<note place="margin">Matt. 15.</note> our ſauiour teſtifieth of them ſaying, in vaine doe they worſhippe me, teaching for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines mens precepts. And the Lord by his Prophet ſayeth, who hath required theſe things at your handes. But ſuch we commende vnto the people as are preſcribed vnto vs of God in his holy worke. As it is ſaide,<note place="margin">What works are good. Deut. 6 &amp; 5</note> Thou ſhalt kéepe
<pb facs="tcp:1725:19"/>
the commaundements of the Lord thy God,<note place="margin">Deut. 12.</note> and thou ſhalt put nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, neither ſhalt thou take any thing there from, neither ſhall ye goe there from, either to the right hande or to the left. Ye ſhall not doe euery man what ſéemeth good in his owne eyes. And therefore as S. Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. Ephe. 5.</note> wee exhort men to prooue what is the will of God acceptable and perfect, which is in déede the reaſonable ſeruice of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the which, all other ſeruings are vnreaſonable. For looke whoſe workes we doe, his ſeruants we are: if we doe the works of mans inuention, then are we the ſeruants of men: but and if we doe the workes which God hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then are we the ſeruants of God. Now touching the workes which God would haue vs to walke in, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſpecified by our Sauiour, ſaying, Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was hungry ye gaue me meat,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was a thirſt, ye gaue me drinke, when I was naked ye clothed me, in priſon and ſicke, ye viſited me, &amp;c. And by the Prophet Eſay,<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> ſaying, Ceaſe to do euill, learne to doe good, ſéeke iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1725:19"/>
reléeue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherles, and defend the widow. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Apoſtle Peter ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note> Be ye all of one minde, one ſuffer with another, loue as brethren, be pitifull, be curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not rendring euill for euill, neither rebuke for rebuke, but contrariwiſe bleſſe, knowing that ye are thereunto called,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> that ye ſhould be heires of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. And in another place. Lay aſide all malice, guile, diſſimulation, enuie, and euill ſpeaking. To be briefe therefore, theſe &amp; ſuch like are the workes which the holy Apoſtle haue taught chriſtian people to bee conuerſant in, loue, ioy,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, fayth, méekeneſſe, and temperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Concerning which vertues, whiles our Popiſh doctors in theſe later dayes, haue incombered themſelues much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the workes of their owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they haue ſcarſely ſo much as once thought vpon them. And not this onely, but alſo that which is more abſurd, they aſcribe the goodneſſe of their workes to the power of mans fréewill, or to the habit of vertue, or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of nature, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:1725:20"/>
Wheras in old time men were taught to aſcribe all the dignitie &amp; worthines of their workes, to the faith of Chriſt. For this is the nature office &amp; propertie of faith,<note place="margin">The nature of faith.</note> not only to reconcile vs to God, by procuring vnto vs through the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Chriſt, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and ſo to iuſtifie vs before God in heauen: but alſo here in earth by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing our hearts to bring foorth good workes, and to make the ſame workes acceptable in the ſight of God, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (through the infirmitie and corruption of our nature) were impure and execrable in his ſight. For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is not of faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 14. Heb. 10.</note> is ſinne, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. To this effect our Sauiour ſaith, Make the trée good and his fruit good. For like as an euill trée cannot bring forth good fruit (it may bring foorth faire fruites, and ſuch as to the eye may ſéeme good, but when they come to the triall of the taſte, then it appeareth they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe) euen ſo an euill man (ſuch as all men are by nature and without faith) cannot bring forth good works: he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1725:20"/>
may well bring forth ſuch workes as may ſéeme faire and good, but when they ſhall come to the tryall of the Lords taſte, they ſhall be found vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie. Paul before his conuerſion liued after the ſtrict maner of the Phariſées, and did many faire and goodly workes, yet had he no good works in déed, before the grace of Chriſt had rooted faith in him.<note place="margin">The effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of good works.</note> As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> efficient or formall cauſe therefore of good workes, next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, there is no other but faith. For as a man ſéeth and féeleth by faith the loue and grace of God towards him in Chriſt his ſonne: ſo beginneth hee to loue againe both God and man, and to doe for his neighbour, as God hath done for him. Whereunto Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> beareth witnes in theſe words ſaying,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ioani. e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Like as in the roote of the trée there appeareth no ſhew of beauty, and yet whatſoeuer beautie or comelineſſe is in the trée, it procéedeth from the roote: ſo from the roote of fayth, as from a foundation, procéedeth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer merite or beautie the ſoule ſhal receyue. Thirdly, whereas the word of
<pb facs="tcp:1725:21"/>
God doth not only teach men that their good works are euer vnperfect, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are ſo farre from iuſtifying them that they haue néede dayly to pray vnto God, that he may remit their imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">The end &amp; vſe of good workes. Mat. 5. 2. Pet. 1. 2. Tim. 1. 2. Cor. 9. Heb. 10.</note> but alſo that we are to doe good workes, to ſet forth Gods glory, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our conſciences of our election, to exerciſe our faith, to relieue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and to prouoke others by our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to do the like. They contrarily and moſt falſely teach men, not only to doe good workes, to the ende they may be iuſtified by them in the ſight of God, ſaying,<note place="margin">Tho. Aqui. Hoſius in a. tom. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. cap. 1.</note> that Chriſt ſuffered for origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne, or ſinnes going before bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but the actuall ſinnes, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after baptiſme, muſt be done away by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s merits, &amp; ſo aſſigne vnto Chriſt the beginning of ſaluation, or obteining of the firſt grace (as they call it) but the perfection or conſummation therof they aſcribe to workes, and our ſtrength, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth of holy Scripture, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, There is no remiſſion of ſinnes without blood:<note place="margin">Heb. 9. 1. Iohn. 1.</note> and the blood of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1725:21"/>
Alſo that man being holpe by grace, is able not only to doe all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the law requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, but more alſo. And hereof come the workes of ſupererogation, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie not onely to that principle of holy Scripture, which ſayth,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.</note> If we ſay that we haue no ſin, we deceiue our ſelues, and truth is not in vs: but alſo to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, who hath not onely commanded, but alſo taught his whole church, and euery member of the ſame continually to pray, ſaying: Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes. Thus they derogate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the benefite of Chriſt, and attribute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to works a great or the greateſt part of our iuſtification, directly againſt the veine of S. Pauls doctrine, and firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the auncient Church of Rome, and againſt all the principles of holy Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The tenth Chapter, Of ſinne.</head>
               <p>VVHereas the holy ſcriptures doe teach,<note place="margin">Sinne, what it is.</note> that ſinne if it be rightly defined, is that whatſoeuer in vs by any
<pb facs="tcp:1725:22"/>
meanes is contrarie to the wil and law of God. As the crookedneſſe and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our nature, &amp; whatſoeuer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth thence, as ignorance of minde, lacke of knowledge and true feare of God, the vntowardneſſe of mans mind to Godward, the priuy rebellion of the heart againſt the law of God, the vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liting will of man to God &amp; his word, &amp; whatſoeuer wicked actions, motions, appetits, luſts &amp; deſires flow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For in our fleſh, that is our nature vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat, dwelleth nothing but ſinne: yea the wiſedome of the fleſh is enmitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.<note place="margin">Rom. 7. Rom. 8.</note> The imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of mans hart (ſaith the Lord) are only euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.<note place="margin">Gen. 6. &amp; 8</note> Our newſtart popiſh doctors, not conſidering the déepnes &amp; largenes of ſinne, ſuppoſe it to be nothing els but inward and outward actions with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of will. And ſo thoſe motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are contrarie to the rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if conſent of will be not added, by their cenſure are no ſinnes: and as for originall ſin, by this their doctrine they doe vtterly take it away. For if ſinne can not be, vnleſſe conſent of wil be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1725:22"/>
then muſt it néeds fall out that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne is none at all: becauſe that none doth willingly and by his proper election contract it,<note place="margin">Original ſin made no ſin by the popiſh doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Pſal. 51.</note> contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Prophet Dauid, who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his originall, ſaith: I was borne in iniquitie, and in ſinne hath my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceiued me. Let vs therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe our ſelues (as indéede we are) to be bondmen of ſinne by nature, that being manumiſed by the grace of Chriſt, wée may bee frée, as it is ſaid, If the ſonne make you frée, then are ye frée in déede.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>The xi. Chapter. Of repentance.</head>
               <p>OF repentance,<note place="margin">Repentance what it is.</note> which is nothing els then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion or turning of the whole man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, that is, not onely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked words &amp; déeds, but alſo from fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſts &amp; concupiſcences, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous opinions of God &amp; his worſhip, and from all wicked ſuperſtition, vnto the earneſt ſtudy of perfect innocencie, &amp; ſincere ſeruice of the true &amp; liuing God:
<pb facs="tcp:1725:23"/>
and therfore ſaith the Lord, returne as far as vnto me.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.</note> This y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lateran church of Rome doeth not teach aright, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenor of Gods word, and ancient Church of Rome. For firſt they haue made thereof a Sacrament,<note place="margin">Repentance no ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie not onely to the right courſe of S. Paul his writing, who in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles maketh relation but of two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to wit, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper: but alſo to the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sacrament, wherein accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the definition as well of their owne ſchoolemen as others, there muſt be an externall and viſible ſigne, or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, Let the word be put vnto the element, and then it is a Sacrament: But in penance or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance there is no element, externall ſigne, or viſible ſymbole inſtituted of God, and therfore it is no Sacrament. Secondly, they teach that repentance conſiſteth of theſe thre parts, that is, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, confeſſion, and ſatiſfaction Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, for ſo ſayth the maſter of the Sentences, <hi>in perfectione poenitentiae tria obſeruanda ſunt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punctio cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1725:23"/>
confeſsio oris, ſatisfactio operis,</hi> that is, contrition of heart, confeſſion of mouth, and ſatiſfaction of worke. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition (as they teach) may bee had by the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of frée wil, without the law, and the holy Ghoſt, through mans own action and indeuour: which contrition muſt be ſufficient, and ſo it meriteth remiſſion of ſinne, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the word of God and common experience. For if there were in man either ſuch fréedome and libertie of wil, or power &amp; ſtrength of nature to performe, that when hée would he could deteſt or not deteſt ſin, be contrite or not contrite at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, what néeded then a law to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which (as Ieremie ſayth) is the hammer of God, breaking and tearing in péeces the ſtonie hearts of men, if without the ſame by our owne fréewill and ſtrength of nature, we could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite. And if there were in mans nature any ſuch fréedome and ſtrength, howe chanceth it then that neither the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate can put from them that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition, which their conſciences (will they nill they) ſuffer, whiles the law of God tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb facs="tcp:1725:24"/>
and vrgeth them, as Caine, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, and ſuch like. Neither the elect in their conuerſions could beginne to bee truely contrite, before that by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods law they were humbled. As Dauid before he was ſmitten with the hammer of Gods lawe by Nathan the Prophet, began not to thinke of his tranſgreſſion: And Peter till hee heard the cocke crowe, ceaſed not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Chriſt: neither did Paul leaue off from perſecuting, till from heauen hée heard a voyce, ſaying, Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? &amp;c. Beſides this, the Lord himſelfe by the Prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Ezech. 36. Iere. 24.</note> ſaying, I wil take away the ſtonie heart out of your bodie, and I will giue you an heart of fleſh. And a little after: then ſhall yee remember your owne wickedneſſe, and your déeds that were not good, &amp;c. Where note (gentle reader) howe the Lorde by his prophet in this place ſaith, that he wold giue them a ſoft or contrite hart, &amp; then they ſhould beginne to turne: as who ſhoulde ſay, you haue it not of your ſelues: neither by your owne ſtrength,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1725:24"/>
without my grace, are yee able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your ſelues. And therfore haue the holy men of God bin wont to pray ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Conuert vs, O Lord, &amp; we ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted. Now wheras they ceach that this contrition muſt be ſufficient, &amp; then it meriteth. Conſidering howe odious and lothſome a thing ſin is in the ſight of God, and that nothing in the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall worlde can bee founde (beſides the blood of Chriſt, as of a lambe immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and vndefiled) of ſufficient value to redéeme it with God: what mans life can be long inough, or teares in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die plentie inough, to mourne ſo ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for his ſinnes, that he might me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit remiſſion or forgiueneſſe with God, eſpecially ſéeing our Sauiour ſayeth, when ye haue done all, yet ſay ye are vnprofitable. In confeſſion they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a full rehearſall of al ſins, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Prieſt knowing the crymes, may miniſter ſatiſfaction accordingly. And this rehearſing or reckoning of ſinnes in the eare of a Prieſt (as they ſay) meriteth remiſſion of ſins <hi>ex ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re operato,</hi> that is, the very act doing,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:25"/>
where firſt they require more then any man is able to performe, for as it is written, who knoweth howe oft hee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth? and therefore ſayth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> Cleanſe me, O Lord, from my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret faults. Secondly the Prieſts vſurp and take more vpon them then any where by the law of God is giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For albeit in Scripture wee finde two ſorts of confeſſions of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Twofold confeſsion.</note> whereof one is to God, as Dauid witneſſeth, ſaying, I will confeſſe vnto the Lorde, and thou forgaueſt the puniſhment of my ſinne:<note place="margin">Pſal. 32. Luke 18.</note> and the Publicane, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelfe vnto God, ſaying, God be mercifull to me a ſinner: and this kinde of confeſſion to God is alſo of two ſorts,<note place="margin">Two fold confeſsion to God.</note> that is, either priuate, when one priuate perſon priuatly, as this Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane, confeſſeth his ſinnes to God, or els publike and common, when a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and whole congregation make their humble confeſſion together,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 7 1. Reg. 8</note> as 1. Sam. 7.1. Reg. 8. or when ſome open offender, or offenders, doe openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their faultes in the face of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which was much vſed in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1725:25"/>
primitiue time. Another ſort of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is vnto man, as when he that hath offended his neighbour, being touched with remorſe of conſcience, confeſſeth his offence vnto him, and craueth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe. Of this kind of confeſſion our Sauiour ſpeaketh, ſaying, If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue offended thée, reproue him,<note place="margin">Luke 17.</note> and if he repent forgiue him.<note place="margin">Iames 5.</note> And S. Iames, ſaying, Confeſſe your ſinnes one to another, &amp; pray one for another, that ye may be ſaued. As for the popiſh auricular confeſſion, or ſecrete recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp of ſins in the eares of a prieſt, neither hath Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it, nor yet his Apoſtles, &amp; the godly fathers which next ſuccéeded them vſed it. And this ſome of their owne doctors do affirme, as may appeare by the gloſer vpon the decrées, who ſayth, It is better to ſay,<note place="margin">De poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. diſt. 5. cap. in poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.</note> that confeſſion was inſtituted by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine tradition of the vniuerſall church, rather then by the authoritie of the olde or new teſtament. We reade in deede that our Sauiour ſent forth his his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to preach the Goſpel, but no where doe we reade that he ſent either
<pb facs="tcp:1725:26"/>
them or any other to heare ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions.<note place="margin">Auguſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. lib. 10.</note> Yea, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaieth, what haue I to doe with men, that they ſhould heare my confeſſions, as though they could heale mine infirmities? ah curious ſort to know the life of another, but ſlouthful to amend their owne! And <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ſuper Pſal. Miſerere. hom. 2.</note> I bid thee not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thy ſinnes vnto thy fellow ſeruant, that hee might vpbraid thée, but to God that hee might heale thée. And in another place, I doe not bid thée openly to bewray thy ſelfe, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhouldeſt accuſe thy ſelf to others: but I woulde haue thée obey the prophet, ſaying, open thy life vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord.<note place="margin">Io. Scotus. li. 4. ſent. diſt. 7. art. 3.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe thy ſinnes therfore before God. And by the teſtimonie of <hi>Scotus</hi> &amp; <hi>Antoninus,</hi> it had his original by pope Innocent 3. in the councell of Lateran. Concerning that which <hi>Socrates</hi> in his eccleſiaſticall hyſtorie witeth of a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiarie miniſter,<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. 5 cap. 19.</note> &amp; of confeſſon of ſins inſtituted becauſe of the Nouatians, &amp; after vnder <hi>Nectorius Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanus,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked fact of a deacon, abrogated, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the teſtimony of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius, it aperteineth not vnto auricular
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1725:26"/>
confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to that which is required in ſolemne repentance, wherof ye may read in the Tripartite hiſtory <hi>li.</hi> 11. <hi>ca.</hi> 35 Laſtly, where they ſay that this auricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſon meriteth remiſſion of ſins, that is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſt word of God, which ſaith, a man is iuſtified by faith without works, fréely by grace not of our ſelues.<note place="margin">Gal. 2. Ephe, 2.</note> Satiſfaction which they call works not indebted, or of duty, inioined by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy father, &amp; by the which works, not only eternal puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts mitigated: &amp; which ſatiſfactions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope may take away at his pleſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proclaimeth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warre againſt chriſt &amp; his merits, I think it néedles to deale any further therin. This vnſauery &amp; heatheniſh doctrine of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true teching of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. By y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which, repentance co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth theſe 3 parts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition, faith &amp; new life. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in ſcripture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorow of hart, riſing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſideration of ſin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, &amp; of the anger of God prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: which ſorow driueth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to chriſt for ſuccor, whereupon riſeth faith, faith
<pb facs="tcp:1725:27"/>
bringeth afterward amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life, which we call new obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, working fruits worthie of repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>The xij. Chapter, Of the difference betwene the Law and the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>THe Law (I meane the law of God) which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt perfect rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, teaching vs what is good, that we might do it, and what is euill, that we might auoide it, promiſing life to thoſe that abſolutely, and in al and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie point of the ſame fulfil it, but threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eternall death and condemnation to all thoſe, that in any part thereof tranſgreſſe it: differeth excéeding much from the Goſpell, which is the publike proclaiming, denouncing, &amp; preaching of grace, frée remiſſion of ſinnes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall redemption, purchaſed by the mediation of Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Iohn. 1. Heb. 3.</note> For firſt the Law was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Moſes, though faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet a ſeruant: but the Goſpell by Chriſt Ieſus the onely ſonne of God, and true heire of all things. The Law
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1725:27"/>
was giuen with thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, &amp; lightnings,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> and the ſound of the trumpet, and the mountaine ſmoking, ſo that the people in great feare and trembling, fled and ſtoode a farre of: but the Goſpell was publiſhed by the voyce of Angels, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Glorie bee to God on hie, in earth peace, and good will vnto men. The law giuen to teach vs to knowe our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but the Goſpel to heale our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: in the law God ſheweth him ſelf a ſeuere Iudge, but in the Goſpel a moſt mercifull father: the lawe telleth vs that we are debters, the Goſpel ſaith Chriſt hath paied our debts: the lawe ſaith do this and thou ſhalt be ſaued, the Goſpell ſaith, beléeue in the name of Chriſt, and thou ſhalt bee ſaued: the law ſayth, thou art a ſinner, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou muſt be condemned: the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſaith, thy ſinnes are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée, be of good comfort, thou ſhalt be ſaued: the law telleth vs we muſt make ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the Goſpel ſaith Chriſt hath ſatiſfied for vs: the lawe ſaith God is angry with vs, the Goſpel, Chriſt hath pacified him with his blood for vs: the
<pb facs="tcp:1725:28"/>
law ſaith, we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the curſe and malediction thereof, but the Goſpel ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, we are deliuered &amp; fréed by Chriſt Ieſus. As it is written: he aſcended vp on hie,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> he led captiuitie captiue, and hath ſet man at libertie, not to liue as fleſh luſteth, neither hath he fréed him from the vſe and exerciſe of the lawe, but from the malediction and curſe of the law. So that now Paul ſaith, there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirite. And in another place, ſpeaking of the power and dominion of the law, he ſayth, that Chriſt hath taken the obligation writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt vs in decrées, and hath nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it vpon the croſſe, triumphing ouer all, &amp;c. So that as the kingdome of Chriſt firſt began vpon the croſſe: euen ſo vpon the ſame croſſe, and at the ſame time the kingdoome of the lawe expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the malediction of the lawe was ſo crucified vpon the croſſe, that it ſhall neuer riſe againe, to haue any power againſt them that be in Chriſt Ieſus. For like as a woman, when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1725:28"/>
her firſt huſband is dead, being nowe maried vnto another, is quite diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from her firſt huſband: euen ſo we being eſpouſed to our ſeconde huſbande Chriſt, are vtterly diſcharged from our firſt huſband the law,<note place="margin">Rom. 7. Rom. 6.</note> and are no more vnder the law, that is, vnder the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; malediction of the law, but vnder grace, that is, vnder perpetual remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all ſinnes, committed not only before baptiſme, but alſo after baptiſme, &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all our life long. For therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth the grace of God, in not imputing ſin vnto vs, ſo often as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting ſinner riſing vp by faith, flieth vnto chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31. Acts 10.</note> &amp; apprehendeth Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp; remiſſion promiſed in him. This difference of the law and the Goſpel, as it is neceſſarie &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable for troubled conſciences, to be well inſtructed in the ſame: ſo is this later Church of Rome much to blame in this behalfe, becauſe it confoundeth togither theſe two, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nature ſo diuers and contrarie one from the other, imagining y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel to be nothing els but a new law giuen by Chriſt, binding to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes therof, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> condition of our doings &amp; deſeruings,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:29"/>
no otherwiſe then to the olde law, and ſo diuided they the whole after this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into thrée parts, to wit, the law of nature, the law of Moſes, and the law of Chriſt. And as for the Goſpel, (they ſay) it was reuealed for no other cauſe, but to ſhewe to the world more perfect precepts and counſailes, then were in the olde law: to the fulfilling whereof they attribute iuſtification, and ſo leaue the poore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of men in perpetuall doubt, and induce other manifold errours, bringing the people into a falſe beléefe of Chriſt, as though he were not a remedy againſt the law, but came as another Moſes, to giue a new law vnto the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>The xiij. Chapter. Of freewill.</head>
               <p>FOr the better vnderſtanding of this queſtion, we are to conſider three e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, or conditions of man in this world. The firſt of his creation, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect wherof, man was a moſt frée crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for hee was created according to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1725:29"/>
the image of God, to whom nothing is more agréeable than true or perfect frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and libertie: and albeit he were in his firſt eſtate, ſubiect not onely as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and all other creatures, were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the will &amp; ſeruice of God, whoſe ſeruice is fréedome it ſelfe, but alſo to ſome kinde of neceſſitie, as namely to eate, drinke, and ſuch like: yet was he frée from all calamities which might bring death. Hauing his will frée, not onely in reſpect of all coaction or forcing to that which was euill: but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all retraction, impediment, or withholding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which was good: So that by his creation, as there was nothing in him that might drawe or force him to will that was euill: ſo was there nothing that might retract, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw or hinder him from willing, and alſo performing that was good. And therefore in reſpect of this eſtate it is written of him, that God had crowned him with glory and honour. And in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus we reade,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 15.</note> that God at the beginning made man, and left him in the hand of his counſell, and gaue him
<pb facs="tcp:1725:30"/>
his commandements and precepts, &amp;c. he ſet fire and water before him, that he might ſtretch out his hand to which he would.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de nouo cant. cap. 8.</note> Which place <hi>Auguſt.</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Adam, ſaith, God left him in the hand of his counſel: that is, he made him frée both in counſel and abilitie, or able<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power of counſell, that hee might after his owne will, either chooſe the good and refuſe the euil, or els refuſe the good, and chooſe the euill, &amp;c. And hereof hee giueth this reaſon,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de liber. arbit. cap. 2.</note> ſaying, God gaue vnto man in his creation fréedome of will, that he might declare his goodneſſe and iuſtice towards him: goodnes if he had done right, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie of iuſtice if he did euill. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond eſtate or condition of man is in reſpect of his fall. By the which fall, as <hi>Auguſt.</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Ench ad Laurent u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. 30.</note> man loſt both him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his frée will. For when ſinne in the conflict had gotten the maiſtrie, it brought man into ſeruitude and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. For although in reſpect of ciuill and mortall actions, there remaineth in man a naturall knowledge and power of will: yet euen therein men find and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1725:30"/>
proue great difficultie in themſelues, whiles furious iuſt reſiſt morall recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, entiſements and pleaſures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke their ſences: Satan with wicked councellours dayly vrge and enforce them, and God by his wonderfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence diſpoſeth their councels to a farre other end then they had purpoſed. For as Ieremie ſaith, Mans way is not in his owne power: neither can he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect his owne goings. Yet concerning thoſe workes which are good workes in déede, and may bee pleaſing and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, man by nature hath no fréedome and libertie of will. For ſuch woorkes as appertaine vnto the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, and ſo may bée accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and approoued in his ſight, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende vpon theſe two pointes, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge, and appetite, affection, or deſire, both which are wanting in man by nature. And firſt touching knowledge. Notwithſtanding all men by nature haue in them a certaine fourme of knowledge, reaſon, and vnderſtanding: yet concerning thoſe thinges which belong either to his
<pb facs="tcp:1725:31"/>
owne ſaluation, or to the ſetting foorth of Gods glory, the Apoſtle ſaith, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man perceiueth not the things of the ſpirit of God:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. Iohn 3.</note> whereof we haue a ſingular example in Nicodemus, a man not onely indued with good gifts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but alſo furniſhed with the helpe of art: yet when he heard our ſauiour intreating of the miſteries of God, ſtood as a man amaſed, vnderſtanding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And if by nature (as you ſée) wee are rude &amp; ignorant of the things that appertein vnto God: how ſhal we then, or howe can wee either fréely will or rightly performe that wee knowe not. Nowe ſecondly, for our naturall appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, affection, will, and deſire. True it is that all men by nature haue in them an appetite, affection, will and deſire. For as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">Aguſt. lib. 3 Hypognoſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Omni creaturae ineſt illa volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas, qua appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur quod placet, declinatur quod diſplicet.</hi> That is: euery humane crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath in himſelfe a will, whereby he deſireth that hee liketh, and fléeth that he diſliketh. But how this will, or appetite of the natural man, that is, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1725:31"/>
man vnregenerate, is affected towards the will of God, which is the onely rule of righteouſneſſe, that none can decide better then God himſelfe, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth man throughly what he is, &amp; what is in him: who teſtifieth, ſaying, The imaginations of the thoughts of his heart are onely euill continually.<note place="margin">Gen. 6. Rom. 8.</note> And Paul accordeth hereunto ſaying, The wiſdome of the fleſh is enmitie againſt God: for it is not ſubiect to the lawe of God, neither in déed can be. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth right well.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. li. de vocation Gentium. cap. 2. &amp; 3</note> 
                  <hi>Homo à Diabolo, non voluntate priuatus eſt, ſed voluntatis ſanitate:</hi> that is, Man was robbed of Satan, not of his will, but of the integritie or ſoundneſſe of his will. So that there remaineth in man by nature a will: but in reſpect of God and goodneſſe, crooked, peruerſe, and péeuiſh, vnles by the ſpirit through the grace of Chriſt it be made ſtraight, reformed, and reduced againe to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall. And this is the third ſtate of man, called the ſtate of regeneration, In the which ſtate man hath obteined that in Chriſt, which he loſt in Adam,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:32"/>
namely a power not onely to will, but alſo to performe that is good. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it is ſaid, without me ye can doe nothing: ſo likewiſe is it ſaid, I am able to doe all things through the helpe of Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me. For it is God that worketh in vs to wil, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to performe according to good wil. If the ſon make you frée, then are ye frée: as who ſhould ſay, it is but folly to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in any other fréedom. For ſo <hi>Auguſt.</hi> teacheth, ſaying, What can be the frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (I pray ye) of a bondſeruant, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be when he taketh delight to ſin? for he ſerueth fréely that willingly doth the pleaſure of his maſter. And hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he is frée to ſinne, that is the ſeruant of ſinne: and hee cannot be frée to liue righteouſly, vnles being fréed from ſin, he begin to be the ſeruant of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. And a little after. But whence ſhall a man that is bound and ſold haue this fréedome of working well, vnleſſe qe redéeme him, who hath ſaide, if the ſonne make you frée,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> then ſhall ye bee frée in déede? Which thing before it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to take place in man, how ſhall any
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1725:32"/>
man, which yet is not made frée to worke well, glory of frée will in reſpect of good, vnleſſe being puffed vp with vain pride he exalt himſelf: which pride the Apoſtle reſtraineth, ſaying: by grace ye are ſaued through faith. Thus was the originall Church of the auncient Romanes at the firſt inſtructed by the Apoſtles, and afterward by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and others. From the which Sea now howe farre this later Church of Rome hath degenerated, which holdeth and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that men without grace, that is the gift of Gods grace, may performe the obedience of the lawe, and prepare themſelues to receyue grace by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſo that thoſe workes may be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious,<note place="margin">Congrue, Condigne.</note> and of congrue (as they ſay) obteine grace: that is, of good right and equall congruence and agréeance. As if one ſhould ſay, they haue beene good, ſeruiceable and profitable vnto God, and therfore it is méete, reaſonable and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, that he ſhould requite them againe with grace and fauour, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſhould faile in the rule of good congruitie, wherein one part ought to
<pb facs="tcp:1725:33"/>
be anſwerable to another. Which grace being thus obteined, men may (as they ſay) perfectly performe the full obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the lawe, and accompliſh thoſe ſpirituall actions and workes which God requireth, and ſo thoſe workes of condigne, that is, by iuſt law, &amp; equall merit, deſerue eternall life. As for that infirmitie which ſtill remaineth in our nature, againſt the which we are not onely continually to ſtriue, but alſo to pray for mercie, they do not regard it ſo much as once to ſpeake of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>The xiiii. Chapter. Of inuocation and adoration.</head>
               <p>BEſides the former vncatholike, and almoſt vnchriſtian abſurdities, and defections from the Apoſtolicall fayth, touching inuocation alſo they diſſent much, not onely from others, but alſo from themſelues in reſpect of their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall. For wheras in old time the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all perils were wont by ſeruent prayer to flie vnto God onely, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>according to his promiſe is able and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1725:33"/>
willing to helpe all ſuch as call vpon him faithfully: as it is written,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145. Pſal. 50.</note> call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in the day of thy trouble, and I will deliuer thée. Contrarie to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, and example of all the godly from time to time, they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and ſet vp Saints departed to be prayed vnto, and called vpon, as media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of interceſſion, affirming that Chriſt is a mediator of ſaluation, and that onely in the time of his paſſion. Which aſſertion of theirs, how well it agréeth either with the ancient doctrine that S. Paul and the reſidue of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught as well the old Romans as other Gentiles, or els ſtandeth with reaſon and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſe, may appeare by that which followeth. And firſt, whereas they denie Chriſt to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour of interceſſion, howe accordeth that with the ſaying of Paul to the old Romanes, where he ſpeaking of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of Chriſt, ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> He ſitteth on the right hand of God, and maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for vs. Likewiſe in his firſt Epiſtle to Timothie. After his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to prayer for all eſtates,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées
<pb facs="tcp:1725:34"/>
of men, he ſheweth not onely to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhould pray, but alſo in whoſe name, ſaying, There is one God, and one mediator betwéene God and man, which is the man Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">1, Iohn 2.</note> Saint Iohn alſo ſaith, If any man ſinne, wee haue an aduocat with the father, Ieſus Chriſt who is the propiciation for our ſinnes. And our ſauiour himſelfe ſaith, whatſoeuer you ſhall aſke the father in my name,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> not in the name of Saints he will giue it you. Touching prayer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be made vnto Saints, that they might be interceſſors to God for vs, we neither haue commandement that we ſhould do ſo, nor promiſe to ſpéede in ſo doing, nor example of the Patriarches, Prophets, Apoſtles, or Apoſtolical men that euer they did ſo. Which of the olde fathers vnder or befor the lawe, did pray to Noe,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> Abraham, or Moſes, after they were departed. For whereas they obiect the words of Moſes in his prayer ſaying, remember Abraham, Iſaac, and Iſrael thy ſeruants, to whom thou ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt by thine owne ſelfe, &amp;c. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in that place doeth not call vpon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1725:34"/>
thoſe ſaints, that they might make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for him: for then he woulde haue ſaid, O holy Abraham, Iſaac, &amp; Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, pray to God for vs: but by their names he remembreth the promiſes of God made to them. Which of the godly vnder the new teſtament did pray vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy martyrs, Iohn Baptiſt, Stephe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iames, or any other after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Yea, they were obedient to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which ſaith, Cal vpon me: and regarded the promiſe which ſaieth, whoſo calleth vpon the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſhalbe ſaued.<note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> Thus Chriſt hath taught vs ſaying, when you pray, ſay, Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen: and not our Lady which art in heauen.<note place="margin">Ephe. 3.</note> Thus Paul bowed his knées to God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; not to any of the Saints. Thus the congregation in the primitiue church prayed for the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Peter out of priſon,<note place="margin">Acts. 12.</note> not to any of the Saints, but to God himſelfe, and not through the mediation or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of any other then Chriſt. For in thoſe days, &amp; long after, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly neither knew nor taught any other mediatour
<pb facs="tcp:1725:35"/>
then the man Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de vera religi. cap. vlt.</note> As for the Saints departed, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſheweth what is to be done to them, ſaying, they are to bee honoured for imitation, and not to be worſhipped for religion. And <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiph. con. Collyridia. lib. 3. tom. 2. hae. 79.</note> ſpeaking of the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſayth, In déede the body of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was holy, yet not God: ſhe was in déede a virgine and honourable, yet not to be worſhipped, but ſhee did worſhip him, that was borne of her according to the fleſh. They were wont to vſe a poore reaſon, taken from the ſimilitude of an earthly king: vnto whom men cannot haue acceſſe but by officers in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées. As though God were like to a mortall man, and had néede of a gard to ſaue him, or of officers to informe him. When the ſcripture ſaieth he knoweth all things, yea euen the very thoughts of men: and is more readie to heare our praiers then we are to make them. Nowe whereas they make Chriſt the mediatour of ſaluation, how agréeth it with commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſe and reaſon that they appoynt other interceſſors, ſéeing ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is in Chriſt. For ſaluation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1725:35"/>
once had, what can wee require more? or what lacketh he more to bee obteined of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints, which is ſure to be ſaued only by Chriſt? And yet in their Catholike denotations they teach men thus to pray to the bleſſed virgin, Saue all them that glorifie thée. What mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell though they agrée not with vs, when they are contrary to themſelues? Here vnto alſo apperteineth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of reliques, and the falſe ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Sacraments, that is the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſignes for the things ſignified, contrarie to the worde of God,<note place="margin">Deut. 4. Luke 6.</note> which ſaith, God onely is to be worſhipped.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>The xv. Chapter, Of the Sacraments, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>THe corruptions and errours of this later Church of Rome as touching the Sacraments, are neither ſmall nor yet a few. For firſt, by the inſtitution of Chriſt, and ancient obſeruation of the godly, there are but two Sacraments of the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to wit, Baptiſme,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:36"/>
and the Lords ſupper, they haue added vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiue other ſacraments. And for better profe hereof, the Apoſtle Paul in all his Epiſtles maketh mention of no ſacraments beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramental Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, &amp; Baptiſme, or waſhing of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Ianuarium Epiſt. 118.</note> And <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith, He hath bound the ſocietie of the new people together with ſacraments, in number the feweſt, in obſeruation the eaſieſt, in ſignification the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, as baptiſme which is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the name of the Trinitie, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of his bodie &amp; blood. And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de doct. chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana. lib. 3 cap. 9.</note> At this time, ſince by the reſurrection of our Lorde, there hath appeared a manifeſt token of our deliuerie, we are not ouerladen with the burden, no not of thoſe ſignes which we nowe vnderſtand, but the Lord and Apoſtolicall diſcipline, hath deliuered a certaine few, in ſtéed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the ſame moſt eaſie to be done, noble to be vnderſtoode, and pure to be obſerued, as the ſacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the celebration of the bodie and blood of the Lord.<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:1725:36"/>
his booke of Sacraments (if it bee his) maketh mention onely of Baptiſme, &amp; the Euchariſt. Secondly, where as the worde of God hath ordeined theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, not that wee ſhould ſéeke our ſaluation in them: but that by them we might be admoniſhed of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purchaſed by Chriſt, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God might bee firme in vs through faith, and we againe not onely conſecrated to God, but alſo diſcerned from all other people.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> As God gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abraham the ſacrament of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as the ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of the faith, which hee had when he was yet vncircumciſed. And alſo whereas by holy ſcripture we are taught, that neither the Sacraments, do nor yet the worde it ſelfe doeth profite vs without faith, as appeareth not onely by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the author to the Hebrews,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> where it is ſaide, the worde which they heard profited them not, becauſe it was not mixed with faith in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which heard it.<note place="margin">1. cor. 10. &amp; 11.</note> But alſo by the example of the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuing Iewes vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtament, and of Iudas, Simon Magus, Ananias
<pb facs="tcp:1725:37"/>
and Saphira his wife with others,<note place="margin">Iohn 13. Acts 5.</note> who notwithſtanding they both had v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Sacraments, yet were they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the nearer to be ſaued, becauſe they wanted faith. They contrariwiſe teach that the Sacraments doe not onely ſtir vp and confirme our faith in vs: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that they auaile and are effectuall without faith, by the verie doing of the action, without any good motion of the doer. As is to be found in Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quine, Scotus, Catharinus, &amp; others. Thirdly, beſide manifold abuſes which they commit in the ſacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, by adding to the ſimple words of Chriſts inſtitution diuerſe other newe found rites, &amp; fantaſies of men, where the old Church of Rome was wont to baptize men onely, this later Church of Rome hath baptized Bels, and haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the words of baptiſme to water, fire, candels, ſtockes and ſtones. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as concerning the Lords Supper in the primitiue Church, as appeareth by the example of Chriſt, and teſtimonie of S. Paul,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> the vſe then amongſt them was, to haue the participation of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1725:37"/>
bread called the Lords bodie, and of the cup called the Lords blood, adminiſtred not at an altar (as now it muſt needes if it pleaſe the Pope) but at a plain boord or table, where, not the miniſter alone did receiue, and the other looked on, but the whole congregation together did communicat with reuerence &amp; thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing. Yea,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ad Eph. ſer. 3. cap. 1.</note> if any did abſteine from the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, and would be but a beholder onely, the old fathers and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome in the primitiue church, (when as yet the priuate Maſſe was not hatched) did excommunicate him as a wicked perſon, &amp; an Ethnicke.<note place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecra. diſt. 2. cap. ſecularis. De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecra. diſt. 2. cap. peracta.</note> And therefore in old time Calixtus decréed, that after conſecration all ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, vnleſſe they had rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the Church: for ſo haue the Apoſtles (ſaith he) ordeined, and ſo doth the holy Church of Rome hold. And as the whole congregation did communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate together, ſo alſo did they partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate in both kindes, for ſo Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles euery where taught,<note place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecra. diſt. 2. cap. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perimus.</note> and the old Catholike fathers &amp; biſhops followed. And if any did otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:1725:38"/>
as <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſaith) hee was counted to commit ſacriledge. And it was not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a ſtrange language which the congregation vnderſtoode not, but in a vulgar &amp; common ſpeach, that it might be vnderſtoode of all, as is witneſſed by S. Paul, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded that al things ſhould bee done in the Church to edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but what edifying can bee there, where the people knowe not what is ſaid.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 4. de vita Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> And for this cauſe godly Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine cauſed the Scriptures to be placed in a legible hand in Churches. And <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian</hi> in his 127 conſtitution, ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that all Biſhops and Miniſters ſhould ſound out their ſeruice, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the myſteries, not after a ſecrete maner, but with a loud voice, ſo as they might not onely be heard, but alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode of the faithfull people, which could not bee if they had ſpoken in an vnknowen tongue. Herevnto might be added the teſtimonie of <hi>Hierome, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> and others, but for breuitie ſake wee will reſt vpon the teſtimonie of <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Innocent. 3. offi. iud. ord. c. quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> niam.</note> who ſaith, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in many partes within one citie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1725:38"/>
and dioces, much people of diuerſe tongues are mixed togither, hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one faith diuerſe rites and maners: we ſtraitly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, that the Biſhops of thoſe cities or dioces, prouide ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent men, which according to the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of rites and tongues may celebrate among them the holy functions, &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the eccleſiaſticall ſacraments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them by word, and alſo by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Yea and this they did alſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lifting ouer the prieſts head, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping, or knéeling, or knocking their breaſts or any ſuch like thing. Only gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thanks for the benefite of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, &amp; praying vnto God for his continuall fauour and grace towardes them.<note place="margin">Platina in vita Sexti.</note> As <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of <hi>Sextus</hi> witneſſeth of the Apoſtle Peter, that he miniſtred the celebration of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, onely with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords prayer. As for the new found deuiſe &amp; terme of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, it was not in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue time, nor many yéeres after, til the councell of Lateran 1059. as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> teſtifieth, ſaying, The Church hath latelye defined tranſubſtantiation.
<pb facs="tcp:1725:39"/>
A long time it was ſufficient to beléeue the true bodie of Chriſt to be preſent,<note place="margin">Li. annota. 1. Cor. cap. 7</note> either vnder the bread, or any other way.<note place="margin">Lib. ſenten. 4.</note> Likewiſe <hi>Iohn Duns</hi> ſpeaking of the words of inſtitution, ſayth. Theſe wordes of Scripture might be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more eaſily, and more plainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tranſubſtantiation. But the church did chuſe this ſenſe which is harder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto moued (as ſéemeth) chiefly becauſe men ſhould holde of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the ſame which the Church of Rome doth hold. And after, in the ſame place, hee expounding himſelfe more plainely, maketh mention of Pope In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent the third, and of the councell of Lateran. For our Sauiour when hee inſtituted that myſterie, meant not by chaunging the elements of bread into his bodie, or of wine into his blood, to worke a myracle, but by ordaining a Sacrament, to leaue a perpetuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of his death, till his comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Io. cap. 6.</note> And therefore ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the bread and wine are both the ſame things they were before, and alſo chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into another. Meaning they are the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1725:39"/>
ſame they were before, in nature and ſubſtance, and changed, in reſpect of vſe and propertie. And <hi>Gelaſius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De ſacra. li. 4. cap. 4.</note> the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread, or the nature of wine ceaſe not to be. And <hi>Theodoret.</hi> After ſanctification,<note place="margin">In Dialog. 1. &amp; 2.</note> the myſticall ſimboles or pledges looſe not their owne proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for they remaine in their former ſubſtance, figure, and forme.<note place="margin">In ſermo. ad infantis.</note> And <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi> That which you ſée is bread, and the cup, which alſo your eyes ſhew you: but as touching that which your faith requireth to bee inſtructed in, the bread is the body of Chriſt,<note place="margin">De conſecr. diſt. 2. cap. qui mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</note> and the cup his blood. And <hi>Origen,</hi> That bread which is ſanctified by the word of God, in reſpect of the matter or ſubſtance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the bellie, and is caſt into the draught. And Chriſt himſelfe not onely after the conſecration, but alſo after the communication ſayth,<note place="margin">Luke 22.</note> I will drinke no more of the fruite of the vine. Now the fruit of the vine, is wine and not blood. And in ſpeaking thus we derogate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the Lordes ſupper, neither doe wee make it a bare ſigne, as ſome falſly ſlaunder vs. For we affirme and
<pb facs="tcp:1725:40"/>
teach that Chriſt is truly preſent in his Sacraments, in Baptiſme that wee might put him on, in his Supper, that by faith ſpiritually we might eate him, and through his death &amp; paſſion might obteine euerlaſting life. For although wee rent not Chriſt in péeces with our téeth, yet we poſſeſſe him in faith, mind and ſoule: and therfore when we come vnto the Lords table, we haue not our mindes fixed vpon the creatures, but lift vp our mindes thither, where Chriſt our true and onely foode is. And ſo the councell of Nice commandeth, ſaying, Haue not your minds baſely faſtned on the bread and wine. And <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, ſaying, we call the body of Chriſt a carkas, and we muſt be Egles, that we may know how we muſt mount a loft if we wil come vnto the body of Chriſt, for this table is for Eagles, and not for Iayes. And <hi>Cyprian,</hi> this bread is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> food of the mind &amp; not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belly. And <hi>Augu.</hi> in another place ſaith, how ſhall I hold him as abſent? how ſhal I thruſt vp my hand into heuen, that I might hold him ſitting there? He anſwereth, ſend vp thy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1725:40"/>
faith, and thou haſt holden him. But for theſe our new found Romaniſts affirm and teach Chriſts body, fleſh, blood, and bones, as he was borne, crucified, and buried, to be in their little round cake. Therfore they worſhip it, they offer it, they eate it, or elſe they cloſe it faſt in a Pixe. Where if it corrupt and putrifie before it be eaten, then they burne it to powder and aſhes. And notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they know right wel by the ſcriptures, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt can neuer corrupt or putrifie: yet will they néeds make it the body of Chriſt, &amp; burne all them for heretikes, which with them wil not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that, which is againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an beliefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>The xvj. Chapter. Of Matrimonie.</head>
               <p>MAtrimonie, which is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction or coupling together of man &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in an holy league, inſeparably to cleaue one to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, &amp; to liue togither in perfect loue and vnitie according to Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: in old time w not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counted an honorable &amp; high eſtate,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:41"/>
as may appeare by that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Hebrews. Where it is ſayd, Mariage is honourable among all,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> and the bed vndefiled: But alſo was freely permitted to all ſorts of men, that were apt therunto, and had néed of the ſame; as it is written,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> to auoid fornication, let euery man haue his wife, and let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry woman haue her huſband. But now the newe Catholikes of the Popes Church, repute and cal mariage aſtate of imperfection, and preferre ſingle life be it neuer ſo impure, before the ſame: pretending that whereas the one reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, the other filleth heauen. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pope Ciricius in his decrées, citeth that ſaying of the Apoſtle, to wit, they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> againſt thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are lawfully ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. And for this cauſe they haue of late dayes (not regarding whether they had the gift of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencie or no) through coacted vowes reſtrained many, both men and women, from holy wedlocke, not to the filling of heauen, but rather to the ſtuffing vp of hel. For from hence haue procéeded, adulteries, fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:41"/>
Sodomitrie, with great occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering infants, as we reade of infants heads that were taken vp in pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories mote, by hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds, what time the lawful wedlock of miniſters began firſt to be reſtrained.<note place="margin">Anno. 600.</note> By which occaſion the ſaid pope Gregorie reuoked the canon he had made a little before, inhibiting the lawfull mariage of miniſters. And Pope Pius the ſecond ſaid, he ſaw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſes why miniſters were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained of mariage:<note place="margin">Platina in vita Pij. 2.</note> but he ſaw mo &amp; greater, why they were to be permitted to marry. Yea this is moſt certain, that the nearer we come to the ancient time of the Church, the leſſe ancient ſhal we find the Romiſh doctrine in this point. And to beginne with the Apoſtles, and their owne examples &amp; canons: who although they were not all maried, yet diuers of them were: and the reſt had power and liberty, to haue &amp; kéepe their wiues, as witneſſeth Paul, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> haue we not power to lead about a wife being a ſiſter, as well as the reſt of the Apoſtles. Albeit <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> which was 200. yéeres after Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:42"/>
denieth not, but that Paul was maried beeing an Apoſtle as well as Peter and Philip. The Canons alſo which are ſaid to be the Apoſtles, ſay, If any teach y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a prieſt for religion ſake ought to contemne his owne wife,<note place="margin">Can. Apoſt. 6. Canon.</note> let him bee accurſed.<note place="margin">Anno. 180.</note> In the yeare of our Lord 180. we read of Policrates Biſhop of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who diſſenting from pope Victor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a certaine controuerſie of Eaſter day, alledgeth for himſelf, how his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors before him ſeuen together one after another, ſuccéeded in that ſtate, &amp; he now the eight, was placed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place. Vſing this diſcent of his parents, not onely as a defence of his cauſe, but alſo a glory to himſelfe. In the Nicene councell,<note place="margin">Anno. 400.</note> when ſome went about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine miniſters from mariage, Paph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius a godly father, himſelfe béeing vnmaried reſiſted the ſame. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe before this,<note place="margin">Anno. 300. Gangren. Concil. diſt. 28.</note> the councell of Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gren, which was <hi>Anno.</hi> 300. did eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the libertie of prieſts mariage, as a thing both good and godly. Moreouer, procéeding yet in times and Chronicles of the Church, we ſhall come to the ſixt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1725:42"/>
councel,<note place="margin">Concil. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. diſt. 35. cap. quoniam.</note> called the councel of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, almoſt 700. yéeres after Chriſt. The wordes of which councell be alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the decrées, and be theſe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Becauſe in the order of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Canon, wee knowe it ſo to bee receyued, that ſuch as be Deacons and Prieſtes, ſhall profeſſe themſelues to haue no more copulation with their wiues, we following the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the diligent Apoſtles, and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of holy men, enact that ſuch lawfull marriage, from hencefoorth ſhall ſtande in force, in no caſe diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their coniunction with their wiues, neither depriuing them of their mutuall ſocietie, and familiaritie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in ſuch time as they ſhall thinke conuenient. Hitherto you haue heard the Decrée: heare nowe the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, in the ſame Decree and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction conteyned. If anie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall preſume agaynſt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Apoſtles, to depriue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſt or Deacon from the tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and companie of his lawfull wife, let him bee depriued. Finally,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:43"/>
here in England till the comming of Anſelme in the dayes of William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,<note place="margin">Guiliel. Malmsb. li. 1. de geſtis pont.</note> and king Henrie the firſt, &amp; of pope Hildebrand 1067. the reſtraint of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters lawfull mariage was not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely eſtabliſhed for a law. And as it was not yet entered in here, no more was it in many other places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. For <hi>Auentinus</hi> a faithfull writer of his time,<note place="margin">Exact. ſyno. Mediola. Anno. 1070</note> who writing of the councell of Hildebrand, ſaith, Prieſts at that time had publikely wiues, and did procreate children as other Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Gebuilerus.</note> One of the Popes crew teſtifieth, that in the time of the emperour Henrie 4. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1057.<note place="margin">Anno. 1057</note> to the number of 24 Biſhoppes, both in Germanie, Spaine, &amp; France, were maried, with the Cleargie alſo of their Dioces. Pope <hi>Symmachus diſti.</hi> 80. ſaith, let Prieſts be reſtrained from the conuerſation of all women, except it be their mother, ſiſter, or their owne wife. Where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloſe in the margent gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this note, Here he ſpeaketh accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ancient times. Truly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that verified in this later church of Rome, which ſo many yéeres ago
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1725:43"/>
Paul prophecied &amp; foretold of, namely that in the later times there ſhoulde ſome depart from the faith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> hearkening vnto ſpirits of error, &amp; to the doctrines of deuils, forbidding to marrie, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to abſtain from meats, which the Lord hath created, to be taken with thankeſgiuing. To conclude therefore, mariage in it ſelfe is either good or euil: if it be good, why do they forbid it: if it be euil, why do they make a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>The xvij. Chapter. Of Magiſtrates and ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</head>
               <p>AS concerning Magiſtrates and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill gouernment, what hath bene in old time the iudgement of the godly, may manifeſtly appeare by that which Paul writeth to the Romanes, ſaying, Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> for there is no power but of God: whoſoeuer therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receiue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues iudgement. Where firſt it is to
<pb facs="tcp:1725:44"/>
be noted that the Apoſtles would that euery ſoule ſhould be ſubiect to his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full magiſtrate. Which words <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> (as hath beene alreadie ſhewed) expoundeth of Prieſts, Monkes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, and what ſoeuer. For if any pretende to bee exempted becauſe hee is ſpirituall, let him conſider, that none euer had ſuch abundance of the ſpirite as Chriſt: and yet was he ſubiect to the ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. And if holineſſe of life coulde diſcharge men from obedience to ciuill rulers: who more holy then the Apoſtles, and yet in ſuch things as appertained vnto the function of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Magiſtrate, they did not onely themſelues, but alſo taught others to obey,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note> as Peter teſtifieth, ſaying: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues to all maner of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man, for the Lords ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be vnto the king as vnto the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour.<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> &amp;c. And Paul writing to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſayth, Put them in remembrance that they bee ſubiect to principalities and powers, and that they bee obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. All this notwithſtanding the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1725:44"/>
of this latter Church of Rome with their clergie, howſoeuer they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and boaſt themſelues to be the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, yet in this matter of ſubiection and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ciuill Magiſtrates, they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept no inſtance in any. Secondly, whereas it is ſaide, that there is no power but of God: learne thereby with <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> to diſtinguiſh betwéene the perſon and the function. For the power or authoritie is of God, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt néedes be good: but the abuſe or miſuſing of the power or authoritie, is from the corruption of mans nature, and the malice of Satan: as the Lorde complayneth, ſaying,<note place="margin">Hoſc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> They haue reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but not by mee, that is, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my will and ordinance, but according to their owne luſtes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites. And yet wee are not to thinke but euen ſuch perſons are not onely for good cauſes ſtirred vp of God, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their inordinate procéedings direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the wonderfull prouidence of God to ſuch end as hee knoweth beſt. And yet neither God to bee made the
<pb facs="tcp:1725:45"/>
authour of euill, nor they the authours of any good. For although God gaue the perſon, and ſtirred vp the party that woorketh euill, yet God neither woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the euill himſelfe, nor yet in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the perſon, or ſtirring vp the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, had any reſpect vnto euill, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which is good, both in reſpect of the profite of his Church, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncing of his owne glorie: as God gaue Pharaoh, not that hee ſhould doe euill, but that his name might bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in him. And although Pharaoh (as all other tyrants) did all thinges not to the ende he might pleaſe God, but to the ende hee might pleaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, yet God by his vnſpeakeable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, whereby he draweth light out of darkeneſſe, and turneth all that for good, which he did onely for euill. The good therefore that commeth of their euill gouernement, is altogether to bée imputed to the prouidence of God, who directeth and turneth their ſtudies, councels and labors to a far other ende then they intended. So that though in reſpect of the effect and end, they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1725:45"/>
but that God would haue done, yet do they offend grieuouſly in doing of the ſame, becauſe they regard not the will of God in doing of it, but to ſatiſfie their own wicked and vngodly deſires. And as their ſtudies, councels &amp; labors haue another ende then they either knewe or intended: ſo ſhall they alſo haue another rewarde (not then they haue deſerued) but then they looked for. Finally, where it is ſaid, Whoſoeuer reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receiue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues iudgement. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are taught, not onely how magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhould be obeyed, that is, more of conſcience, becauſe the worde of God bindeth vs thereunto, then for the feare of puniſhment, becauſe we cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. For though the magiſtrate were vnarmed, &amp; a man might prouoke and contemne him fréely, to wit, without puniſhment for it, yet is it no more to be attempted, then if we ſawe preſent vengeance to beat hand for it: but alſo we are generally taught, what end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for all thoſe that fight againſt
<pb facs="tcp:1725:46"/>
God in reſpect of his prouidence to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the world by magiſtrats and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, namely, a iudgement, that is, not onely in iuſt, but alſo a moſt ſure ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance what way ſoeuer it come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>The xviij. Chapter. Of Purgatorie.</head>
               <p>THe Paradoxes, or rather the fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the later Church of Rome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning purgatorie, be monſtrous, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther old nor apoſtolical. For firſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Scriptures and worde of God, make mention onely of two places af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> As it is written, hee that beléeueth in the ſonne, hath euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, and he that obeyeth not the ſonne, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> And Iohn Baptiſt ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſayeth, Hee will gather his wheate into his garner: but will burne vp the chaffe with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenehable fire. In which words you ſée mention to bee made of two places onely &amp; two ſorts of people: beléeuing, or not beléeuing, chaffe or wheate, ſaued
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1725:46"/>
or els damned, in the Lords garner, or els in fire vnquenchable. And the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers for the moſt and beſt part of them, either vtterly denie that there is any third place, or els ſpeake of it verie doubtingly,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Enchir. ad Laurentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. 69.</note> as <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in his <hi>Enchiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion</hi> to <hi>Laurentius,</hi> ſayth, It is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible but ſome ſuch thing may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life: but whether it bee ſo in déed, or not, may be a queſtion. And in the ſame worke, Chap. 67. hée ſayeth plainely, that hée thinketh them to be deceyued which doe beléeue, that they who depart out of this life in their ſins, can by fire be clenſed in the life to come. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> likewiſe taketh away pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie.<note place="margin">Epiph. lib. 2 haereſ. 59.</note> And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo in his booke <hi>de bono mortis, ca. 2. Gregorius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in his dialogues <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39. writeth doubtingly of it. And in his booke <hi>de eccleſiaſt. dogmat. cap.</hi> 77. <hi>&amp;</hi> 78, maketh no mention of it. But in his booke <hi>de fide ad Petr. cap.</hi> 2. conſtantly denieth that there is any place for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance after this life. And in his fifth booke <hi>Hypognoſt.</hi> ſayeth after this ſort. The Catholike fayth through
<pb facs="tcp:1725:47"/>
diuine authoritie, belongeth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen to be the firſt place, and hell to be the ſecond place: a third place we know none at all, neither doe wee find any in holy Scriptures. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his firſt tract againſt <hi>Demetrianus,</hi> ſaith, after a man is departed hence, there is no place for repentance, no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ſatiſfaction, life is either loſt or woonne here. Yea, there is nothing more vſuall, and common among the olde fathers then this ſaying. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude I with that exhortation of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in a ſermon that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth againſt drunkenneſſe, ſaying, Let no man deceiue himſelfe, brethren: for there are two places, and the third is not ſéene. He that reigneth not with Chriſt, ſhall without doubt periſh with the deuill. Yet our newe Catholikes haue not onely found out a third place, which they call Purgatorie: but alſo teach, that lacke of beliefe thereof brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to hell. And this Purgatorie in torture &amp; paine differeth nothing from hell, but onely that it hath an ende, the pains of hel haue none. The fiery paine
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1725:47"/>
whereof (ſay they) fretteth and ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth away ſinnes before committed in the body. Contrarie to the which, holy ſcripture teacheth, ſaying,<note place="margin">Iohn 1. &amp; 2</note> The blood of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne cleanſeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſinne. And in the ſecond Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle, ſpeaking of Chriſt, he ſaith, He is the atonement for our ſins, and not for ours onely, but alſo of the whole world. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Now there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Ieſus. And <hi>Reuel. cap.</hi> 14.<note place="margin">Apoc. 14.</note> Bleſſed are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead that die in the Lord, they reſt from their labors. But if they go from this world to purgatorie, they haue but ſmall reſt. The paines of this painted fire indureth in ſome longer, in ſome ſhorter time, according as their ſinnes haue deſerued, which time being expired, then God of his mercy tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to heauen for Chriſts ſake. But firſt they muſt abide in that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie fire, ſo long till it haue cleane fretted and ſcowred away the ruſtie ſpots of euery ſinfull ſoule, vnleſſe they be cleanſed by the Popes pardons and indulgences, ſacrifice of the altar, diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:1725:48"/>
and trentals, prayer, faſting, meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious déeds out of the treaſure houſe of the Church, almes, and charitable déeds of the liuing in ſatiſfying Gods iuſtice, &amp;c. And for all the pope can (as they teach) deliuer the ſouls out of that wofull paine of purgatorie, which is ſo great, that if all the beggers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world were ſéene on the one ſide, and but one ſoule of purgatorie on the other ſide, the whole world would pity more that one then all the other, yet is this prelate ſo mercileſſe, and hard harted, that he will not rid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. But he knoweth right well, that if the people ſhould beléeue, that either there were no purgatorie at al, or els vnderſtand that the popes good grace had put out the fire of purgatorie, then would the chimneis of his kitchin ſone ceaſe to ſmoke. For the ſmoke that commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fire of purgatory, is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially conueyed through the Popes chimney. Beſides theſe, ther are many other falſe erors, &amp; great deformities, which abound in this later Church of Rome. Howbeit (gentle reader) theſe may ſuffice to let thée ſée, not onely how
<pb facs="tcp:1725:48"/>
farre they are fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, but alſo how néere at this day, through the grace of Chriſt, we come to that ancient faith, religion &amp; profeſſion of doctrine, which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in Rome, but alſo in England and other kingdomes of the world: and that this reformation here in England (as in other parts of the world) is not a falling away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith of Rome: but rather a reducing to the true &amp; ancient faith of Rome. The eternall father and God of al mercy grant vs for his chriſts ſake grace co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to grow vp more and more in thankfulneſſe towards his maieſtie for the ſame, that whiles Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land doth liue, the truth of his Goſpel may neuer die. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God and moſt merciful father ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all thy wayes, and true in all thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which neuer faileſt them that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call vpon thy name. We heartily thanke thy diuine maieſty, for that it hath pleaſed thee of thy great goodneſſe, to heare the prayers, and grant the petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of vs thy vnworthy ſeruants, which, then with ſorowfull and heauy hearts we powred out before thee, when our enemies approched to deſtroy vs and our countrey. And
<pb facs="tcp:1725:49"/>
foraſmuch (O Lord God) as thou haſt vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vntill this preſent day, not onely to preſerue vs, our Queene, and realme, from the laying in wait of many and mightie aduerſaries, both at home by ſecret conſpiracies, and abroad by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein inuaſions: but alſo vnder a moſt gracious &amp; chriſtian Queene, haſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs helth, welth &amp; peace, with liberty of bodies &amp; minds, now by the ſpace of xxx. yeres. Moſt humbly we beſeech thy fatherly goodnes to graunt vs grace, that in word, deed and heart, we may ſhew our ſelues truely thankefull and obedient to thee for the ſame: and that we may continually growe vp more and more in thankfulneſſe towards thee. That like as by thy deliuering of vs, thou haſt declared thy ſelfe to be our mercifull God &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: ſo we alſo by our ſeruing of thee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy moſt holy worde, may ſhewe our ſelues to be thy faithful and obedient ſeruants. Maintaine (O Lord) and increaſe the honorable eſtate of our gracious ſouereigne, and al hir no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble councellors &amp; magiſtrates, with the whole body of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, let thy fauour ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them, thy holy ſpirit ſo gouern them, that thy true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be purely maintained, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners reformed, ſin &amp; ſuperſtition reſtrained, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preciſe rule of thy ſacred &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly word. Conuert or elſe ſubuert all thoſe wicked ſtudies, counſels, and practiſes whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the deuill or man doth worke againſt vs. Comfort thoſe that are afflicted with any kind of croſſe or tribulation, &amp; ſpecially thoſe which ſuffer for the teſtimonie of thy truth. Grant thy Goſpel a free paſſage, and ſend vs euerlaſting peace in Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1725:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
